[Music]
okay
it's december 23rd 2021 nicera cool
ceremonial lighting
it's the end of 2021
paper review stream
so welcome to active inference lab
we are a participatory online lab that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at some of the links here on this slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve on our
work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams
this page shows
a snapshot of our website which i'll
also put in the youtube live chat and
head over there if you want to
participate in 2022
and check out this coda site if you want
to see more information
on our past and upcoming live streams
today the
active 21 paper review
we're going to just be reviewing and
reflecting
some of the fun times and interesting
things that we've talked about this year
and
just like a dot zero is just an
introduction not a review or a final
word this is gonna be just even more so
because we're gonna spend like literally
two to three
minutes two to three memes per paper
and we talked about them for several
hours so this is just going to be kind
of
an off the cuff thought per paper not
a total rehearsal of the paper
and
this should be really fun so sarah and
dean thanks a lot for joining maybe if
each of you would like to
say hello and just what
made you excited to participate today or
what would be one kind of overall
thought to to lead us in here
go sarah
oh man
the pressure okay i have been around for
a while so like my brain is not fully
dialed but um
i actually was just reviewing some
michael uh mike 11 videos
and
um
oh boy my brain is about as exploded
re-watching them as it was the first
time so um
you know that like looking at life
through like an agential point of view
versus looking at it through this like
homeostatic i'm just my brain cannot
hold at all that's where i'm starting
oh yeah my name's sarah by the way
cool dean
hi yeah hi uh i'm dean
uh the reason why i wanted to do this is
because
when i was doing programming
pre-retirement one of the one of the
things i found to be really really
really helpful
was what we call the learning exhibition
where
there was a timeline a chronological
review and
there was a lot
of time given over in front of what we
described as a
significant audience to be able to give
people a chance to take
the entire breadth of what they'd done
and sort of go through it themselves and
pick out the highlights
and then a lot of light bulbs went off
in the in the learner's mind and so
for me even though i haven't been
participating throughout this year i've
only been about maybe 30 to 40 percent
of the livestreams i still find that
review process to be really really
helpful in terms of
getting me some sense of where i am
because as we said in the i think it was
the
paper or
yes i think it was a 34 paper it matters
where you came from so this gives me a
chance to kind of look at that and um
give myself some sense where the
directions are going next
great
yeah we don't have any papers at all
selected for 22
so it'll be like
a fun fresh start
so yeah for each of the papers well
first we're gonna go just look at the
videos that are not paper live streams
and just see if any we wanted to recall
but then for each of the papers we're
going to just talk about like what were
our memories if we read the paper or if
we went to the discussion or listen to
it how did our perspective or generative
model change from that discussion or the
paper
and then third question what ideas or
themes happened in the paper that came
up later or touched upon something we
went into later and then also the last
question how does the paper or the
concepts in it or the claims change how
you thought about something or did
something
so we'll start with just looking through
the non
live stream videos so you can be total
either you can bring up one of these if
you want to highlight one of these guest
streams
that you uh liked
we had 13 guest streams or just total we
can both pass but the guest streams are
just
uh research related to active inference
and so we hosted a really global
range in many different sectors of
one-off guest streams
from 13 different people
and these are like always open if
somebody wants to do one themselves or
wants to
recommend that somebody do one so
uh do either of you want to highlight
one of these streams
danny can you remind me who is the
gentleman from australia that was
talking about sort of the uh philip
garrens
philip guerins okay
depersonalization and cote qatar
syndrome
yeah okay that that one i
that one i found particularly
interesting just because he brought up
things that i wasn't even aware existed
so
okay sarah
okay we're past no worries okay we had
the model streams which are
math and technical
walkthroughs or uh
exposition so the first four one point
one through four was ryan smith and
christopher white
that was awesome
i mean it's like a 10 hour series so
it's kind of a fun
course there
and then a few others so these were
really fun and we hope to have more of
those and then the last category was the
org stream we had one of those with
richard barlett
about any kind of organization
and then we had three math streams sarah
we had great times in math streams
i think it was maybe even your idea to
do the first
one
so
it was different for me yeah
yep fun times so
we're here to talk to about really the
live stream
series and so in the live stream series
we met once per week
basically every week
and we spent
about two weeks per paper so a dot zero
video would happen at some point before
the dot one and that was background in
context and then at the regular weekly
times we had a dot one and a dot two
which were group participatory
discussions
sometimes the authors joined other times
the authors didn't join
and we had a few
dot threes or higher where we really
made an extended series and this allowed
us to
have a lot of time to go into different
ideas so again today we'll just kind of
take one
favorite meme this is like the haiku
form of the papers
but
it's just awesome how many um
perspectives people brought
and the papers that we got to read
and just exploring it as a new format so
cool times there any other
comments before we jump into the uh
marathon
just just one quick one i really like
than the previous slide i really like
richard bartlett's coming in and the
idea of that work stream because i think
he really wasn't sure what
what we were on about and i think we
brought a lot of things to his attention
not just it was that that felt like a
very um reciprocal
uh conversation and the other thing
isn't in the
when we had the zero one two and when we
had
authors with us
um
[Music]
i think i can't speak for them but i
think that again
when we had those kind of interactions
with people and they got a sense that
they weren't just sort of writing to
to the clouds if they were writing to
real people who are really wanting to
have a real conversation with them i
thought that was um
as the year went on i think
maybe we're gaining a little bit of a
reputation for
for um
sort of making these things
a little bit more available and a little
bit
more interesting because we can have a
conversation about it not just leave it
in the script
i agree
that'd be awesome anyone who wants to
come on and
visit or
discuss their paper or share their
perspective so we're gonna jump in
to the papers so um either of you or
anyone in the live chat just
totally feel free to
just
ask a question or to give an observation
and all of the papers
if you want to
follow along
then go to the coda which i'll put into
the youtube live chat again at the coda
you'll see the link to all the papers
but also we'll have each paper will be
seen with um like the title and the
authors okay so
here we go
rewind your clock
spin your
arrows of entropy and time
it's now january 2021
early yonder
and we started with the paper
in 13
integrating cybernetic big five theory
with the free energy principle a new
strategy for modeling personalities as
complex systems and that was by adam
saffron and colin deyoung
so the aims and the claims the paper
were essentially
connecting
fep free energy principle and ai active
inference with another
kind of clade of theories and that was
the fusion of cyber genetics
the goal directed systems and big five
like the psychological descriptive
features so cb5t had already integrated
cybernetics with big five by seeing the
big five axes of trait variation as
being part of cybernetic systems rather
than some other kind of system
and then this paper
extended that into the free energy
principle in active domain
and just to show one figure which or
table which we'll do from each paper
this was table one and it just makes a
very uh clear laying out
of the correspondences between
the
traits and the terms that are used in
cb5t
and then the
the terminology and the ontology of
active inference and how those terms
exist
so
um it was a fun beginning of the year
because it had to do with personality
dynamics and about the connections of
domain specific and domain general
fields and how active inference could
play a role in all of them
so either of you want to add a thought
on this paper
okay so that was paper 13.
paper 14 was
the math is not the territory
navigating the free energy principle by
mel andrews
so this was a single author philosophy
paper so very different format than some
of the ones that we read other times in
the year
and
this paper um does an awesome job with
the mimetics of the title
but it
really makes awesome historical
contributions
and also there was latter versions of
this paper that were updated after our
discussions and through other
interactions in the community
and also other works by mel so
just like many things it's kind of part
of a bigger
picture
but here the project is to trace out the
historical and the philosophical
threads that constitute free energy
principle and active inference
and so it's kind of interesting because
i know these terms will come up in later
papers
thinking about for example the helmholtz
decomposition
of a gradient field into a solenoidal
curl component
and an irrotational divergent component
so this idea came up in the historical
antecedents and the philosophical
threads that play into the free energy
principle but it was being approached
from a philosophy perspective so it was
a fun discussion we talked about the
history and philosophy of fep about what
is science
and about
how does the work of scientists
and discourse
with that of philosophers
so it's a fun paper any comments on this
paper
i got a question for you daniel can you
give me a spoiler alert did you resolve
the second bullet on slide on this slide
here
in the when you guys were discussing
this this one certainly not like
anything like a theory a law a
hypothesis or a research program
yeah
yes so i think
i forget the terminology of the paper
but it's like target models versus
target list models
and there was some discussion about
how
it's uh
a source of hypotheses
in a
in a different way
than research programs of the past
and yeah it was a cool
paper
and it feels like the only thing my
brain can retain about that was that it
was like
free energy principle is like an api
and how you apply it is
how you apply it
yes i think this introduced
a lot of like the api isn't the
territory it's an interface
agreed and for other domains how do
philosophers
interact with this object
what is their what is their
uh intellectual api for all of this api
it's a programmatic interface
so it's just execution critical it's a
yes i'm like that i don't know yeah
let's look it up because that's
yeah application programming interface
it calls
so you can like call a certain function
from a different program
okay
okay so 14.
we've moved from personality to
history and philosophy of thermodynamics
we then had a very
important discussion in 15 with free
energy principle computationalism and
realism a tragedy by thomas van s
hippolyto
so this paper
differentiated
what they called a realist approach
and an instrumentalist approach
and it's actually amazing that these
terms
came into play and heard from stage left
very early in the year
but it was a theme that
certainly came out again and again
during the year
and
to get to their figure here's their
conclusion of their paper
in this paper we have defended the
instrumentalist take on the fep arguing
that the realist approach is a
non-starter regardless of whether it is
representationalist or not
so they kind of make this two by two
which is in a table in their paper but
we illustrated it as a
quad quadrants here and so the left to
right is realist versus instrumentalist
like we're really talking about the real
state of the system versus we're using a
statistical instrument to measure and
model systems
and then
there's an orthogonal axis
with
representation and non-representation
and this paper
comes out
ambiguous or neutral or system specific
on the representation axis
but it
um
disfavors the realist side
and says that the instrumentalist side
is going to be possibly very productive
so
um in other words
some of the claims that the fep and
active make
might be consistent with us using them
as statistical instruments or models but
not necessarily describing quote real
features of the real world
so that was definitely a theme that came
up again and again in the year
and one of your favorite themes too dean
yeah
yeah well
so again
i'm going to go back and look at this
one because i didn't know that you'd
done this
um
but so question for you um
when they talked about realism
um
[Music]
are they saying that
what are they saying there of what what
how are they describing what is real
i think the realism in instrumentalism
was in respect to the term generative
model
so the generative model is literally
implemented by a human brain to
calculate the potential states of the
environment
so that's kind of like
brains are doing active inference
or brains are doing predictive
processing
versus
it could be just a insightful
statistical description
that doesn't need to be the same as the
basis of the underlying process
so like you could use a linear
regression on brain data without the
claim that that's what the brain is
really doing it's not really doing
linear regressions it's just that we use
that statistically so when we use an
active inference model to describe data
is that what the system is really doing
realism or is it just a clever
statistical tool that we're applying and
that's instrumentalism
so can i ask you one more quick question
because i know we got a lot of papers go
through here have you seen the movie um
sully
no
okay well that sullenberg had to land
the plane on the hudson river
and he had to make a calculation when
the when the bird strike hit
so would how would these authors view
his calculation in terms of
picking a place where he had to land
would they say that that was
instrumentalist because he was using
instruments
and he did land didn't land in new
jersey and he didn't land back in
in laguardia so how would how do you
think they would
how would they play that scenario in
terms of their argument in this paper
so
the idea of using instruments it's also
it's related to um
extended cognition
and like humans using technology
and
instrumentalism can still be approached
when there's real lives on the line
so
um
[Music]
let's just imagine that
uh the pilot was using some sort of
heuristic and some sort of back of the
envelope calculation
and based upon a falling parabola
that's instrumentalism because it's
being
used just as a
insightful statistical description
rather than
necessarily a description of the system
itself which is like realism
so maybe i need to see the movie though
and yeah i know you should it's a it's a
great movie and b i actually used it in
my program because i actually thought
that it was some combination of the two
there's the real situation and then
there's the instruments to tell you what
how far you can go so i'm just curious
i'm going to go back and paper now
kristin and others um i believe have
called that kind of a structural realism
like there's not a denialism that there
is
statistical regularities in the world
so it's not like a sort of pan denialism
it's just a qualified recognition that
we're only going to be able to use
observations and we're not going to be
able to map hidden states and there
might be special cases where we can but
we need to prepare for the situations
where we can't
and um in the chat in respect to solely
sid wrote his decision was mostly
intuitive instrumentalism over years of
internalization is indistinguishable
from realism
very wise by sid so let's go to 16.
16 we
switched gears to um wanja visa and carl
firsten's paper and ronza joined us in
these discussions
on the neural correlates of
consciousness under the free energy
principle from computational correlates
to computational explanation
so this was another example it's kind of
like 13 of taking a topic that's an
important debate or an ongoing area of
development in some area like
personality sciences or
um neuroscience here and then see what
can be gleaned or added by fusing it
with fep
so the neural correlates of
consciousness
is people looking at how different
anatomical and functional and
informational aspects of systems are
associated with their capacity for
awareness
and it's a a big area
we kind of reviewed a few different
ideas about it in the videos
to summarize up
the
argument and the
contribution of this paper they wrote in
short it may be more useful to consider
the system from the point of view of the
extrinsic information geometry
probabilities encoded by internal states
then from the point of view of the
intrinsic information geometry the
probabilities of internal states
so we talked about what that meant and
what the implications were
about
whether
the systems with um conscious awareness
were those that had potentially some
kind of informational signature
in how they worked like
a slot machine there's going to be some
sort of statistical description of it
and is there something that might
differentiate a slot machine's actions
from a human pretending to be a slot
machine
are we just
in a world where we can never tell or
might there be some sort of
way that with the right statistical
analyses there'd be some feature
and of course that
um leads us to questions like what is
alive what is awareness what is
consciousness suffice to say they were
unanswered but we had really cool
discussions and
explored how a few different formalisms
from active and fep could play into this
basically eternal discussion so any
thoughts about this paper
okay
we stayed in the kind of
trippy and
interesting science domain
with the paper of fields and glazebrook
called information flow in context
dependent hierarchical bayesian
inference
so chris fields came on for 17.1
and it was really a memorable discussion
and 17 was also where we met shawna
dobson
chris fields collaborator
and
this paper
uh was
really using active inference more in
the discussion as sort of like a
concordance or a harmony
and less of a fundamental
building block of the paper
and
they in this paper used the concepts of
quantum contextuality and category
theory
and bayesian inference
to put them all
together
into a new way of
modeling systems it doesn't look like i
pulled out a second image for this one
but they had the cones and the co cones
and it was all about
frames and meaning and semantic flow and
it was just a very interesting
discussion
any
memories from those discussions yes
sarah
yeah i um this was the first time and
this was in my last my first year of
this graduate program that i'm in
philosophy of science where i learned
about the frame problem
and um it's
really like i it's like once you see it
you cannot unsee it and now
it's like it can i see that constraint
and everything and i i'm not sure if i'm
thankful or if i hate him for bringing
that up because it's like
it's terrible it's a tyranny
what if you like were to summarize the
frame problem
or why it matters or how it relates to
acting what would you say
um
i mean
really
kind of a layman way of putting it but
it just
you
it's like contextuality you can only get
so much information you like with a
particular perspective you only the
information versus
context ratio in some sense is fixed is
how it
it's kind of like a woo-woo way of
putting it but um you know when i think
about it even with the paper we'll cover
later um
like 11's problem like you can slice the
problem on the time axis or the state
space access or like but you you're
always slicing it you you can never
get the full picture that's what it
feels like
dean what does that make you think about
well i i i walked in out of the
wilderness on this paper this was my
first encounter with
with you folk and uh
i'm still putting my head back together
because
my my head blew up and i'd pick up all
the pieces and reconstruct it
so again i always try to bring it back
to the simplest examples and and i and i
agree with sarah for me
this speaks to why there's such a thing
as as change blindness like why you
can't count the passes the basketball
passes and see the dancing bear at the
same time
no matter how much you try to take in
there are upper and lower limits
and this this just when i as soon as i
saw this i was like
oh my goodness
if sarah said you can't unsee it
i was just like we will i don't know if
you're going to be a slide here with the
moth the flame but i just flew right
into the flame at this point that was it
it was over because i was
i didn't realize that people were
talking about this stuff and it was
really cool
i just pulled one of the slides just so
we can kind of recall that so it was
like about these um graphical images
and then there was um
[Music]
it's kind of like a way of looking at
programs it's a structure that
represents programs but also other
things too with the two spaces now it's
the whole discussion right like what is
the scope what kind of systems are we
talking about here and then there's like
the sort of coherent system in a given
perspective
and then there's the case where like two
perspectives are looking at a given
set of classifiers the a sub letters
and so that could be like
the the person at one point and the same
person at a future time point but like
if the memory is in a different frame
and it doesn't have the same semantics
then like the memory changed but then if
memory does have the same semantics
there is some invariance so then what is
the structure of that invariance and
then
this isn't the math review stream but
with shauna dobson this is where we were
going the whole
time crystal diamond
infinity perfection diamond sheath
um
area which was like a i was just like
glad to have heard it from
i hope that we can
like fill in some of the
structure underneath that
as individuals and as a group
to
better approach those ideas because they
were
interesting
okay
so on to
18.
all right so 18 we
met back up with christopher and ryan
who had done the model stream one
four-part model stream on the
step-by-step
um
guide to active inference and here they
joined us for more of a research
discussion
on their paper the predictive global
neurano workspace a formal active
inference model of visual consciousness
so this was fun because it was uh some
colleagues that we knew christopher and
ryan and i kind of knew how we operated
a little bit
and then we were talking about
consciousness
but
in a very operational or instrumental
way whereas the previous uh visa and
fristen paper was much more about like
the metaphysics of consciousness even
though that was also being approached in
somewhat of an operational way
but this paper was very much focused on
the neurophysiological observables
and the specific access consciousness
which is specifically just the parts of
consciousness that we can report on
and then
they kind of like paper 13 took a big
idea in neuroscience which is the global
neuronal workspace the gnw model
and the predictive
anticipatory predictive processing
paradigms kind of took the fusion
previously of those two ideas like
cybernetic big five and then combine
that with active inference so we're kind
of like seeing some
scaffold structures mad lib structures
by which people are contributing to
active inference research and also
staying integrated or bridging with
other fields
and the
one of the figures that really
summed up this paper
was figure three this is a bayesian
network description of the generative
model with arrows showing the
dependencies between the hidden state
factors and outcome
so each one of these nodes is like a
variable of different types
so the level one outcomes
are um
visual on the left side
and then on the right side there are
things that you say verbal report
i see a square or i didn't see anything
it's kind of like a linguistic state
machine for action and then like a
visual state machine for input
and then
there's this attention modulating
precision
about how the visual level one outcomes
get mapped through that a matrix to the
level two outcomes
and so the sense states of level two the
outcomes
are the hidden factors relative to level
one so that's like very much the kind of
hierarchical bayesian modeling that
we've been talking a ton about and then
this is like the inference
combining the level two factors
as well as information about the trial
number
and then that is what kind of allows the
model to swing back from sensing like a
square and red
and then making inference on it being
like a red square or whatever it is
and then that arcing back into
the um
inference on linguistic structures
so it was a very
integrative paper
and uh
cool
topics that we had brought up even
already like consciousness and visual
awareness
and
using
specific models to
test hypotheses and make unique
predictions and experiences
so
any thoughts on that
i think what i took away from this was
because this was the second paper that i
participated in and i realized very
quickly that in order to be able to get
some traction and be able to
show how things are working they were
really really
really really small
uh windows that
the researchers were looking at it were
really short relatively really short
time frames otherwise you don't get any
traction so i i i
i quickly understood that if if you're
going to
if you're going to be able to do
something with this you have to take it
one piece of the puzzle at a time you
can't take all thousand pieces at once
um if you if you want to be able to say
something that you can actually defend
otherwise you're you're
you're inferring instead of being able
to show the empirical evidence
yeah it's almost like yeah you can infer
you can predict you can even look
20 miles ahead but you got to take
one step at a time
with your body and that can be like slow
and painful
because it's easy for your mind to race
out way in front
oh i could have been here already if
only this had happened or i can imagine
myself at the top of the mountain yeah
but
you gotta act and so this was sort of
the kind of work that we
love to see
so
paper 19.
this was
deeply felt affect the emergence of
valence in deep active inference
by casper hesp smith parr allen fristen
and ramstead so 2021 paper and this was
kind of like fun because
we were just discussing papers
weeks after they were published like
fun to just be in the loop at that speed
and i kind of remember that for this
paper because
it
um
combined
a few different things that people had
said about active inference for a long
time which was first off it can deal
with affect
and anxiety and metacognition and the
second one that um
there could be a deep temporal planning
so not just instantaneous gradient
minimization like moving your eyes to
the dimmest or most uncertain part of
the image but like
moving to the part of the image that
wasn't the most uncertain now but was
predicted to be the most uncertain that
is what is called temporally deep active
inference
and this paper
did that they
had some beautiful images
and they
specified
and encoded
generative models for affective where
anxiety was an affect
active inference where this beta and the
gamma
are like the precision and the inverse
of that which is like the um ambiguity
they're like kind of one over each other
beta and gamma so whether it's high
precision or low ambiguity or vice versa
how that uncertainty variable
plays into the free energy minimization
given c the preferences and e the
affordances on pi policy
and that's what allowed the organism to
do these temporal rollouts
so it's like at time point one
it was doing prediction on time point
one two and three at time point two it
was still doing it on one two and three
and that could be either um it like
doing kind of retrodiction
or it could just be doing um some time
horizon of forward looking or some
combination thereof
but they showed some really
provocative patterns
like when there's a deep temporal roll
out
with a high variance and possibilities
like things could go like ninety percent
of time we go well
five percent of the time they're amazing
and five percent of time they're just
like deathly
that can lead to anxiety
because every path will have some lethal
possibility but that's like walking in a
city like
you can't
do the every possible rollout
and so that's a theme that came up which
was when we're applying active inference
how do we do
principled rollouts so that we can do
computation that's effective
whether that's because we're more on the
affect management side or whether
because we're on the computational
efficiency
angle in either case having uh adequate
roll outs is really important
so it was a cool paper
dean or sarah any thoughts
i i got a quick one i think where this
was really interesting for me is that
even though things were laid out in a
step-by-step
like a step-word way in order to be able
to explain what
casper and the other authors were
looking at it it introduced the idea
that
as you mentioned already daniel that
there was availability
factor as well
feelings determine what you made
yourself available for
not just how precise or how much
attention you could give over to
something so although the way that they
showed the model was
step step step sequentially
um the affect piece of it said so what
even if you're present and even if
you're counting out the number of time
steps
what else is what else is going on here
not and talking with casper about that
was i thought quite
enlightening yeah
awesome discussion
so paper 20
we
discussed the emperor's new markov
blanket by yelle brumberg
and christophe delaga and joe dewhurst
emmanuel baltierri
so this paper was cool it was on our
markov blanket theme
as well as our
qualified criticism
and improvements of
active and fep
this paper
did two things as they lay out they want
to they also did something similar to
paper 14 andrew's paper with a bit of a
history of science recap of kind of how
we got here which came up in axel's
paper 34 but this is more of a
philosopher's how we got here history
story
and they traced the development of
marcon blankets from bayesian statistics
through
to where they got to where they are in
active inference
even though the
actual citation history i believe well
much more will be learnt that we know at
this point
and then they talk about
the philosophical implications of
different
perspectives on what markov's blankets
are so they conclude
either you stick to the original
uh innocuous but metaphysically
uninteresting formulation of blankets or
it's bolstered with novel metaphysical
and probably also perception and control
theoretic math um premises
as we saw some of those premises were
indeed fulfilled in 2021 with paper 26
and paper
32.
some but not all of the criticisms are
still really important though
and we talked about the um distinctions
between like a generative process
the actual causal structure of the
environment that gives rise to
observations like that's the actual
ecosystem where it's raining
then there's the generative model which
is the agent's generative model of
that ecosystem for example
and then also the difference between a
posterior density and a variational or
recognition density which we're not
going to go into but this plays into the
difference between
using inference with a model
versus within a model
so like the scientist is applying the
linear regression that's doing inference
with a model but then like
the universe that they're in
if you're thinking of that it like is
the model itself so it is also related
to a little bit like realism and
instrumentalism
so it was a great
philosophical and important um
socio-historical critique pape
also yele was the first person who i
ever heard about fep from
him and tobias
in the summer of 2015.
so
that's kind of cool that
he was able to join and that we were
able to reconnect
and
that he's still working on those topics
and sharing his important perspective
any comments on this one
yeah so
the with and the within part is really
interesting because if you inference
with
that kind of lends itself to the
traditional sort of academic perspective
of a framework but if you're within a
model
and you're trying to
see yourself
not just with within the sort of your
your
your focal limits but knowing yours that
you're embedded how that changes things
at the time that we took this paper up i
wasn't really paying much attention to
this because maybe because i already
kind of was
thinking of active inference in both
in both ways being sort of inside and
also
framing something so i was selecting out
what i wanted to pay attention to but
one of the things i will say about ellie
is i've read three of his other papers
because we've made them available
and
not just a prolific author but brings up
really good ideas
great
so on to 21.
so 21 this was a fun
series this was with john boyk
so john boyk who will be like
a
active lab advisory board member in
2022 and got more involved in the dot
tools organizational unit and like
really contributed a lot like it was
awesome just to get involved with him
this way
so he had written a three-part
science-driven societal transformation
series it's really like a three-part
small book but in these three papers
and
they
talk about applying active inference
across multiple scales and
socio-technical structures
and i picked out this slide
because this one instead of a regular.0
where like a few of us will kind of
collaborate and do
just a quick run through the paper
he and i did a four part dot zero it was
dot zero one zero two zero three zero
four
with this
long jamboard sequence
where he really broke down the whole
paper
and we walked through the whole jamboard
and just did a really long
lead up
and he talked about social
transformation and about how active
inference plays a role in that in
multiple different capacities
from the integrated systems modeling
to
[Music]
how we
um think about
social systems i don't
um
even think we can go into the sub
details but also it was cool because it
was like a work in progress
as any proposed
r d slash transformation platform would
have it
so this was a fun discussion with john
boyk and it's cool that we got to work
with him a lot this year
any comments
okay wasn't part of that no
that was fun though okay so 22.
i think i remember if not both of you
then certainly you were 13. so 22 was
with uh alex kiefer single author paper
from 2020 called psychophysical identity
and free energy
so this paper had a target thesis
that biological systems
are those whose internal states come to
encode statistical models as a result of
spontaneous self-organization in
response to environmental pressures
so that kind of like adaptive
self-organization it's not a
fep only take
however this is where the real
fep
hypothesis comes into play
which is that
those systems learn and make use of
their models by minimizing their
physical free energies
so that brought us to a discussion about
minimization of free energy and life
and so we talked about
there's systems that are at equilibrium
and then they're systems that are sort
of infernos and then there's the
controlled burns
and
all of these systems are kind of playing
the free energy minimization game
so we talked about
what kind of equilibrium
is living versus non-living what is the
boundary that we're looking for order or
disorder to be shaped within
what time scales phases temperatures
metacognitive processes matter
and alex
was a very willing converse aunt
and um do either of you have any
memories from this discussion
other than the fact that he was bringing
identity in which
i think sometimes we
we can focus in on on the car the the
continuation aspect of it or we can
what he brought up was
how how can we see
identity playing
playing along or playing nicely with the
free energy principle
yep
so good
all right 23. so this isn't kind of the
middle of the year so this paper was a
2021 paper in synthesis called
embodied skillful performance where the
action is by anes hippolyto manuel
balteri carl firsten and maxwell
ramstead
so
dean
why don't you just describe the paper
well no because that's it's not because
you know as a parent you're not supposed
to pick your favorite children oh but
but it's pretty obvious what my favorite
was so
uh rather than be biased i'll let you
talk about it a bit all right i'll give
i'll give the um i'll give the bad cop
version no um it was a great obvious uh
paper
really brought a lot to the lab in the
discussion so what they did was they
talked about
control theory and several historical
frameworks for control theory
including what they called
instructionism the idea that motor
commands are passed like kind of
telegraph messages to the motor plant
which is kind of the operative physical
actuator
they also talked about theories of
optimality so that was kind of theories
of
information transmission and control
and they tied that to theories of
optimality specifically like after motor
control theory
they then contrasted those traditional
or at least non-active inference models
of control
with active inference and they argue
that active inference does not need to
posit the instructionist assumption
rather it can be interpreted as an
interactionist account which was
something we went a lot into
and just to dig one layer into detail
before dean love to hear more
we talked about um
[Music]
how active inference challenges optimal
motor control theory
and the way that it frames sensory motor
back to active
behavior
and just one cool meme that i think
stayed with us was traditional omct
accounts of behavior can only specify
performance using a single number a
scalar that is defined and consequently
tracked by a value function
so here is the greedy hill climbing
robot
on the just trying to find out the
gradient but of course if you just go up
the gradient
then you get trapped in local maxima and
how do you balance reward and learning
and development and so yes reinforcement
learning reward learning they have all
kinds of heuristics and totally
functionable
things that they do to get around some
of those traps like local maxima and
learning bias
but
what was very fascinating in this paper
was to take an embodied skillful and
cultured perspective
and combine that with a different way of
thinking of this
surface that landscape and the agent
doing inference on the landscape
thinking about it in terms of the
irrotational curl free component and the
solenoidal divergence free component aka
the helmholtz decomposition
and then thinking about what that
decomposition
meant and did
in the context of this interactionism
that active inference brings rather than
the instructionism which is implicit and
explicit in these optimization driven
awful motor control theories
what do you think about that dean
you know i just i can remember going
back through the paper and just like
cheering cheering them on
because
i think that they laid out a really good
argument
at the end of the day what this paper
for me
asked
without getting into sort of the
technical parts of it was
how soon
do you bring the material
into the into the interaction so
when i say the material is something pre
something pre-designed or something
pre-formatted or already
you know somewhat organized and even
when we talked to carl in june and he
was talking about the edu
aspects of active inference there was
still some question around
are there are there consequences for
bringing plans forward too quickly in
terms of what that
means in terms of a cost if we are
building a generative model
and how does that how does that affect
things um are we
are we helping people by
making things
making things in finger quotes simple or
are we
in in some ways manipulating them
instead of allowing them to be the
manipulators of what's
what happens next
so i again if if
if the way that we
this year or the parts that i
participated in which included point
zero and a point one and a point two
emphasize the part of interaction as
opposed to just simply
somebody preaching and another person
being in the in the choir
um i thought that this paper was
saying was reinforcing the some of the
methods and some of the ways that
and processes that we've enacted
so i was really really appreciative of
that
yeah a lot of the discussions about
education and about the course and about
onboarding and accessibility and
learning of active inference and the
ontology development we really brought
this idea back
like are we
interacting with people who who know
different
or less or more or are we instructing
and
how does that
change the system's design and
hint it changes everything
okay
oh i thought we said no spoilers for the
right yeah okay so 24. um this was a
paper by dimitri markovic and uh
stochick sarah schwabel stefan cable
the paper was called an empirical
evaluation of active inference in
multi-armed bandits so dimitri and sarah
joined for the discussions and that was
really awesome
what this paper did it was a lot more
like a traditional machine learning
paper in its structure
they provided an empirical comparison
between active inference
and two other state-of-the-art machine
learning algorithms the bayesian upper
confidence bound ucb
and optimistic thompson sampler
and they applied these three different
algorithms the active and the two other
machine learning algorithms
in
two different challenges the stationary
and non-stationary multi-arm bandit
problem
which kind of maps on to like basically
being at a casino and figuring out which
slot machine has the best return through
time
kind of like investing type problems but
also maps onto a ton of different other
domains
and here's a representative figure 5
where they were
looking at those different algorithms
the thompson sampler bayesian confidence
bound and the approximate active
inference agent
and then they were looking at the case
of the switching multi-arm bandit so the
rewards were changing and the difficulty
was non-stationary
and so um
listen to the discussions and read the
paper for more but there were certain
cases not every single case but certain
cases where the active
agent did really well
so that was cool because it just sort of
showed a path
for a kind of paper which
i hope we have a hundred thousand of
these papers and frameworks that make
these kinds of results
more accessible
because it was like
hey
if you're working on this kind of
problem
maybe try this kind of model out
so that could be kind of cool
and this discussion we talked a lot
about the technical aspects
and some of the code side because we had
talked a lot about philosophy
metaphysics and activism
we had talked about some of the math and
the analytic modeling
and this is where we talked about some
of the numerical and computational
elements of active inference
okay
sarah's back for 25.
so 25 was
the computational boundary of a self
developmental
developmental bioelectricity drives
multicellularity
in scale-free cognition by michael levin
sarah do you want to maybe
summarize the paper
or give just your overall thoughts on it
um i don't know that i could ever do
justice on a summary but i think the
thing that i took away
um
from it or the thing that felt like a
novel kernel of thought that was like
in the name of brain conservation the
only thing i wanted to take with me
was this um
this idea he had of um
of
a cone as a as a as a kind of a
conserved quantity between different
ideas of the individual or different
species or cell level like however you
want to construe the individual
that you that um
this
creature living form of some sort
uh has an ability to imagine versus an
ability to enact um and that those two
kind of opposing
or orthogonal um considerations are
somehow possibly conserved
uh between different levels of organism
and i just thought that was brilliant so
that was like the big thing for me
yes so there was the one figure with a
bunch of different there was the aliens
and the ant and the flea and the human
with the different cones and we talked
about time cones
and then here was
a slide from questions for 25 2
and so there's this example
of the ant colony and it's like which
one of these levels is alive or scales
or however you want to call them like a
cell
the nest mate the ant the colony
it's like well the cell will survive if
you put it in the right media for this
amount of time but the nest mate will
survive if you put it in this media for
this amount of time okay but then the
colony survives lifted from its
environment only for this amount of time
with this kind of stability it's like
where are you gonna stop are you gonna
just you know pull out new mexico and
put that into a test tube so what is the
living system
and um
how do we talk about systems that have
radically different cognitive
architectures
what is the role of bioelectricity
in
rapid
basal cognition the kind that might be
influencing the formation of cancer
and development and biofilms
so just
yeah and so you and blue did an awesome
job on these streams
yeah blue did an awesome job but it i
really enjoyed it oh my god his ability
to like
extrapolate from a thousand different
points of view
just wow it was great
and i really like that he doesn't um
you know he's not it might seem in the
paper that he's like making a commitment
to to what an individual is or whatever
but in fact the way he's what he's
trying to propose or how he's trying to
think about it
um
is is resisting that temptation um to
commit to you know this this living
that's not and things like this it's
it's wonderful it's a good good way to
to jump into a different paradigm i
think
and also maybe at this point a little
bit more than halfway through the papers
um
thinking of multi-scale individuality
like
everyone who came on was awesome
people did like really well
no one
had any massive unforced errors
so that's like one low bar to clear like
that didn't really happen because that
could be devastating literally
i had literally only two hours sleep
that night i mean it was like the worst
night of my life no not of my life but i
was really and so i was actually looking
at that video the old video and i'm like
did pretty well
for two hours
yeah so
but
beyond just no blundering people really
showed up
and um
blazed way in a different kind of format
where were these journal clubs five
years ago i don't remember them
so everybody who really stepped up and
did it is amazing
and i hope that they like inspire others
and that everybody else feels like
maybe being on a public recorded live
stream is not the exact affordance for
you
that's totally fine
but if you think it is the affordance
for you then
like you should do it
i just wanna i just wanna put a plug in
for like getting
more like
if i could get michael levin and this
guy scott i can't remember his name um
i'm sure he knows about him um but he's
he's actually doing a termites he did
studying termites um
and uh the relationship between these
these living forms and versus how they
you know niche construction how they
affect their environment
um
i just want to i have this
dream of like getting people that have
these complimentary or even a little bit
opposing views in a room and then doing
live streams with those people like like
more than just one person so they're not
just inundated with just their point of
view
we'll facilitate that we'll help anyone
design that and then we'll make the
email thread and make that event happen
if the people want to participate
so 28 or 26 sorry so 26 nice you know a
through z
a good um
number
so this was
basing mechanics for stationary
processes by lancelot decosta carl
firsten connor heinz and uh gregorios a
pavliotis
so this paper as well as 32 which we'll
talk about soon
it was kind of like this
uh left right
one two punch of two very impactful
papers that were submitted in mid 2021
like june ish and then kind of came out
in the end of the year but
these papers
um
let's see in the future looking back how
much they change the game or in what
ways they change the game because of
course there's so much more to be done
and so much different too so
it's not about like evaluating which
ones were super impactful or not
but suffice to say that
26 and 32
took a big
step forward by taking a big step back
and they
took
a first principles look at internal and
external states
and did some very important work to
formalize if not
prove to the nth degree and demonstrate
in every system and
tighten every bolt and everything
but give a unifying
formalism and way of talking about
this idea of the sigma or the mapping
function
between internal and external states
because just the sort of blanket concept
alone
as we heard from several very important
guest streams and other critical papers
in the community um just having
statistical installation of states
of course does not entail that one side
of that blanket or the other is living
or doing inference or cybernetics or
doing anything interesting like at all
and
those who didn't think that were very
optimistic but also they didn't think
through
some of the basic implications of just
mere statistical insulation
and in 26 the mapping function the sigma
brings in the idea that even though the
bayesian graph representation
might have statistical insulation
between internal and external states in
fact that's their definition
there still may
exist for certain classes of systems a
map sigma
that
means that internal states could be at
least acting like they're doing some
sort of inference on external states
which is one of the big pieces that's
required for the active formalism to
have any sort of
not just biological validity or realism
we kind of burnt that bridge back in the
hippolyto days
but just to be like statistically
coherent
so it's like if the linear model
doesn't have internal coherence like the
program doesn't run
it's not like we're having the debate is
the economy a linear model or not we're
saying it's not or it could be but we're
not going to use a linear model to make
that claim
but this is just like at the level of
the linear model working
so this is getting the theory working in
a way where it wasn't
previously
so that was a fun discussion dean any
thoughts on 26
did you um
i don't know if you remember when we had
when we had um conor back in the 32-3
and i asked him
straight up i said so
so when you're looking at this mapping
thing now
are you looking at it at a at a sort of
a tight focal point or are you looking
at the big picture and he said we're
looking at averages
this this was what i was asking because
this paper here
this paper you said game changing i
think what this did is it brought high
definition
i think the game is the game i think the
game is still being played out and
there's still some uncertainties thank
goodness because that's why we're here
but i think the definition and the high
definition and the contrast that this
paper and then and then the
33 paper both of those just the level of
detail they were able to
sort of pull through in those formalisms
and try to speak to what that
synchronizing map
what they believe it is mathematically
that's what i appreciate
with the funny and the high res and the
game changing it makes me think about
like watching tennis
and then
the the tv is better so it's like nope
that tennis ball is just fuzzy
exactly
out of that one
right right and i and i think that
matters because i mean
there's
there's a part of me that wants
there's a part of me that wants to
explore
and there's also things that we don't
need to go over again and again and
again just to prove that we can and i
think that in some of the papers we had
the good fortune of having authors come
back and and say
we i think we can lock this part of it
down
right they're not saying that the whole
thing is is done and complete and and go
to bed now but they there are aspects of
this that we could be pretty
confident
that we we have now of course a
housekeeping
rule was introduced
okay so it's it's not completely locked
down either but there's a there's
certain parts of this now
that we don't have to
guess so desperately i guess that's how
i would describe it yep
so
here was another single author paper of
a quite different type this was active
inference applicability to different
types of social organization explained
through reference to industrial
engineering and quality management by
stephen fox
a researcher
fearlessly unafraid of long paper titles
and
this was a great
set of discussions with
stephen on the streams
so we talked about organizational active
inference and some of his other later
work was even on like auto ethnographic
active inference which is really
fascinating topic for a lot of us
and
we talked about the
quality management system
and about perception action in like
these extended cognitive systems
and
lest anyone think that he was coming on
to sort of speak for the factory farm
approach
there was a very interesting discussion
about craft
and about
how do you have the
mobile and flexible
producing qualities
in systems and have them be regenerative
and participatory
and bring kind of like the high
reliability
attributes of
yes car factories but also like
organisms
high reliability biochemical factories
and then take that sort of a
integrative perception cognition action
approach like we do in active
to
this system so
any comments on 27
yeah i think i think
i think it's time we mentioned
two of our colleagues in particular
because they really stepped up on this
one that's stephen sillan and blue
knight because they they both came in
and they asked some pretty some pretty
good questions and i think i think i
think stephen did a great job of talking
us through his paper
but i i won't forget
steven sillett's question around the
scaling of dead things
and i i thought that was like
that was one of those moments where
um
[Music]
it got really interesting really really
fast so not to say that there
is never drama in holding live streams
but that was a really really good moment
because um
not not every one of these papers is
their complete agreement on and i think
that was one of those times where a
couple of our colleagues really stepped
up and said
you know you know rather than attacking
but just saying please tell me more
because i'm not really sure this is
how we've
sort of evolved the idea of active
inference so far it's
in some respects it felt coming into it
like there was a preforming in order to
be able to make a case but i thought
this author did a really really good job
saying no no no
you mentioned this it was it's not just
on on on grand scales and you know mass
production there's there's aspects to
this that are very much craft based and
i thought he did a brilliant job of
speaking to that he shared his screen
and he
brought up a lot of other resources and
um
yep
we can't name everyone who was on a live
stream go to the code page to actually
see everyone who was but yeah steven
blue
dave
yeah scott david
um
many of you
and others really like
made it super fun like we just had
many of you where we would have like
other research meetings with very
different tone but like we had a ton of
fun
in the streams but we also i think kept
it kind of like on the rails which is
that balance right because
it is recorded speech so 28 speaking of
yeah this was um large sandvik smith
with hesp mataut fristen lutz ramstead
a late 21 paper so this was just again
kind of uh fresh off the presses
discussion with uh lars who came on
and the paper was towards a
computational phenomenology of mental
action
modeling meta awareness and attentional
control with deep parametric active
inference so
we had talked
about the deep
parametric inference previously deep
active inference with the rollouts
through time and about the anxiety and
metacognition we also had talked about
attention with a smith and white paper
about the visual attention so here we
kind of combine those ideas
and we talked about
multi-level bayesian modeling of deep
temporal systems time point one two and
three and that same roll out structure
and now we still have those
uncertainties
those variances
but also we have the second level the
attentional level is now nested inside
of a third level which is this meta
awareness how aware am i of where my
attention is
so again that
first level is like the perceptual level
then the attentional on perceptual
and then the metacognitive on attention
on perception
so that was the probabilistic graphical
model with the deep generative model and
three hierarchical levels of state
inference
so
this was just a um
a fascinating discussion
it just showed how the active inference
structure even just the ones that we've
seen now which are by no means all the
structures we will have
how it allows itself to be nested and
composed here to make really
recursive
strange loop
agents
and so this was a
very interesting paper
yeah we got into the statics and the
dynamics and again we
i
i don't know if i was the only one but
there was also some
some time given over to the again what
am i paying attention to and versus what
i'm what am i available to and and not
just focusing on all of the
attention aspects of it but what's
what's maybe just slightly outside of
that attentional frame but is still
factoring in and influencing
what the go forward or not go forward
move is
so again this was a
casper casper had a couple of pretty
pretty um i would say impressive papers
last year or this year i guess we're not
there yet it's still this year 21.
um we'll do the little of the odd laying
sign karaoke at the end if you're still
dead
okay paper 29 so
i'm 29 years old and we read my paper
for 29
with alex chance maxwell ramstead carl
firsten and axel constant
so the paper was
active in for ants an active inference
framework for ant colony behavior
in this paper we adapted a model that
previously had been used for visual
epistemic foraging on culturally
patterned
pottery motifs
and we adapted that to the case of ants
who could do stigma g so they could
modify their local environment with
pheromone
and then they
use their antennal senses to prefer
pheromone and select actions that would
realize those preferences
and then we simulated those ants in a
multi-agent setting the t-maze test
which is like a common test used in
all kinds of foraging paradigms in the
lab and
um
just like this paper 28 showed that it
was possible to do these recursive
composed nested agents
here
we actually showed for the first time
that it was possible to use active
inference in a stigmatic
context
so not just an embodied inactive agent
or not just one that had a cognitive
policy selection element that was active
inference
but
multi-agent setting where there was also
modification and feedback with the
environment
so it was pretty cool
to talk about
the infra ants paper
and um blue did an awesome job as the
facilitator on this one
and yeah anything you wanted to say on
29 dean
well i was
getting ready to go over to europe so i
didn't get a chance to sort of be on the
live streams but one of the i did i did
watch the live stream you and you and
blue go through it
and one of the things i'm glad you
mentioned the recursive recursive piece
one of the things that i took away from
this was there
not only was there
a function that was looking back on
itself not only was there stigma g which
was something new to me
there was also a kind of a
fractal element to this
and so i as i said i didn't participate
in in the interaction aspect of this but
what i came away from
interestingly enough is i wasn't really
sure whether after reading your paper
whether active inference is actually a
framework
or if it's a process
and so
maybe that's something that we'll
revisit in 2022.
cool question
all right 30. so for 30 we read a single
author paper which was by matthew sims
how to count biological minds symbiosis
the free energy principle and reciprocal
multi-scale integration
so this paper
did some philosophy of biology and then
had a case study of a squid bacteria
symbiosis so we'll just show that to get
at the big idea of multi-scale
integration so multi-scale integration
is kind of like emergent systems
multi-scale systems however the author
here makes the contribution of
differentiating uniscale
from reciprocal multi-scale integration
so uniscale multi-scale integration or
sorry unidirectional
is like
you have the entity
it's the user and then you have the
resources and the resources are like
inanimate so the user could be like some
sort of emergent computational phenomena
invoking
um
dumber
deader computational elements so there
can still be this multi-scale
integration with emergence but the sort
of activity only flows one way even if
there's bi-directional
causality still there's like only a
building up in one direction which is
actually what makes these systems very
easy to talk about in terms of like top
down emergent priors and bottom up
immersions and things like that
and that's in contrast with these
systems where kind of
both ends
are each other's user they're more like
interactive so this is a bit more
of the interactionist instead of the
instructionalism
this is also challenging
notions of just the unidirectional
integration from sort of dumber and more
particle-like to more abstract in
general well that's how some systems are
the unidirectional integrators but the
bi-directional reciprocal integrators
it's kind of like i don't know a rainbow
but it's not just like anchored on both
sides by something that's
of one type it's kind of in a feedback
in a different way
so that was a cool paper a lot of
philosophy and bringing some previous
theories into play like here i remember
that dave
brought up
um
gordon pasque and conversation theory
and that was also a cool thread to hear
about
um
previous systems and cybernetics
theories
and about how active gives us like a new
light on some of those topics what did
you remember from this paper
uh i was
watching you guys and and really
enjoying it because
i had some i had some barley courage i
was
enjoying sunsets in uh exotic places and
and uh what i really liked was the the
fact that as you say the reciprocal
multi-scale integration isn't just
feedback it's feedback and feed forward
and i
you know that whole parallel
uh process a bi-directionality piece i
think it was really important to sort of
make that explicit and say
this is what's this is
this is what sophistication means i mean
it can be less than that but when it's
at this level of
bi-directionality but as you say earlier
said earlier that's a whole different
game
so
yeah kind of wish i was there but i also
was pretty happy with where i was so you
were in a good spot my friend
yeah um okay
so
um stretch all right one
we read the paper from 2021 by patricia
palacios and matteo colombo
called non-equilibrium thermodynamics
and the free energy principle in biology
so this paper was investigating the
statistical physics
historical and conceptual
and dynamical systems historical and
conceptual bases of
free energy principle
they focused on primarily the 2013 life
as we know it carl frist and paper which
is kind of a big target it's like the
death star of fep
um a lot of uh uh fighters have
approached it
even though things have changed a lot
also in the last eight years
right and this paper approaches three
areas
that as we kind of found out in the
discussions like they're not
death nails for fep they're kind of like
critiques where
they're areas where it's good to have
our attention
but that doesn't mean that they're
lethal criticisms nor that they've been
solved either and that was basically the
challenge of the pre-stated phase space
for open-ended biological systems
um the role of erodicity in biology and
the challenge of associating homeostasis
and allostasis behavior with attractors
in those phase spaces so
many of these terms
like about the generality and the
applicability of fep
ergodicity
a lot of themes that came up a bunch of
times in the year
and um
[Music]
some good discussions i remember maxwell
came on this stream and was on others as
well
so um
what do you remember about it or
i was getting
doing
molecular testing and and
i wasn't really participating in this
one yes
good okay 32 so
32 was awesome i'm sure it was um one of
our favorites
yeah it was uh stochastic chaos and
markov blankets 2021 paper
by fristen
heinz
oldstoffer decosta and parr so
this paper we just had the dot three
like a few weeks ago or like last week
right
with connor i think
and it was just
awesome it it got at that kronos kairos
difference
like it's always it's always.3 somewhere
that's the new 5 p.m because it was like
we can always do
another discussion and we could always
have the author share their perspective
or their how they're looking back at the
work now
or if anyone ever loved one of these
papers they could just
do another discussion on it or just
share their view or
it's like always possible to click that
kairos
up by one again
and just build on the past like a
blockchain a little bit
and then um
there were so many figures that were fun
in this paper
but it was about this same coupling
that we've seen a bunch of times
but it did a few different things here
first it introduced that unity is plural
and at minimum two
notion of the coupled systems in the
internal and external states
and then
took on the sort of grand daddy
complex chaotic system the lorenz
attractor
and
did some things with it
i've never seen
which was to
approximate instrumentally
while retaining
the chaotic signature in the iliopanaf
and reframing
this sort of vector field dynamic system
into this decomposed and then recomposed
and partitioned and reintegrated way
that
was just really exciting
what did you think about it dean
well i don't have the math background
and i
i keep bringing that up but
the the thing that i found interesting
is i i learned about the language event
i learned about the lorenz i learned
about the place and i was actually after
after you i'm going to pump your tires
for a second here after you
sort of took the reins on this one and
and try to
explain
in a in a way that was available for
people who may have been watching that
it wasn't just for people who already
have
you know a solid foundation on the map
you tried to explain it in a way and i
think
if there were two papers this year if
you wanted one on the philosophical
piece and if you wanted one on the the
explanation of what the math is telling
us that i think the hippolyta paper and
i think this one i don't i don't really
have a favorite because i think each
each one of these papers brings out an
important
aspect of this whole active inference
realm that we're diving into but this
paper in particular
um
[Music]
wow i mean in in terms of its
in terms of it's trying to
explain
what what the math formalisms are trying
to tell us
if you can
if you don't if you don't get scared off
by that
and it gets scared off by the kind of
arrows going off in all directions piece
it's very informative i don't know that
it's a it's a takeoff point
but if you've been looking at this now
for
as as
formally as long as i have which is
about six months
again this was this was a really big
moment in terms of
sort of filling in a lot of the stuff
that we're hypothesizing about and
making it a little bit more tangible
cool
when i read papers like this i think i
don't have a math background either
that's why
we didn't yeah but i was able to have
conversations with people and
after half after going through this i
was like no this is the
laplace place and this piece and this is
the lorenz piece
right it wasn't just a land it wasn't
just a landman formula anymore there was
actually some and i mean i wouldn't be
able to write it up myself
but actually seeing it now it didn't it
just didn't look like a bunch of
squiggly lines or uh or some kind of an
abstract painting there was actually
some coherence to it yeah like looking
at this and thinking oh this is like
the chaotic flow and the arrows of the
flow and the blue arrows they're
pointing in different directions
here's like the flow on my strategy or
on my approximation
of course if i were over here it would
be a similar flow to if it were very
close and then how do we hold
that highly openiv
chaotic
real flow
even one that's analytically defined so
nicely like a lorenz and then how do we
have it be tractable
yet
retain its essence
and not just sort of like
um you know cut up the cat and then just
go okay well now cats don't move
well i got a better of pullback
attractors i mean i i was while while i
was we were going through this i was
imagining things like so maybe there's a
math to desire lines you know out in the
serengeti or maybe there's a math to the
termite mound
right not just not just in terms of how
we can graph it but in terms of how it
it makes sense in terms of
realizing those patterns in nature as
well
anyway this again this was a
this was pretty
i mean
i guess i'm on full geeks on display but
if you if you like to geek out on this
stuff
this one was a really good paper yep
it was a classic so
fun
paper thanks for conor also for that dot
three
yeah paper 33 good old 33
we uh turned to one of our lab
colleagues to serve all aka aval guaning
for his paper as part of like a really
broad and creative research program
into social and historical dynamics that
he's a part of and the paper was
thinking like a state embodied
intelligence in the deep history of our
collective mind
so
also
as with many many other streams and
papers blue did awesome work on this
paper and presented on some work at some
conferences so
awesome job blue
this paper
made the argument from historical as
well as
sort of um conceptual
bases
that
states
are current
i
i don't even really need to describe
them
that they can be understood as
hierarchical control systems essentially
similar in their core physical
architecture to brains
and avail uses active inference to
ground collective intelligence across
different systems and scales
and the paper
hits on a few different topics which is
kind of outlined by this map
figure that we used in some of our
presentations
and it covered topics related to like
multi-scale embodied intelligence
some of the
anthropology
and historiography
i guess about states and anthropology
just like yeah
areas related to people studies
and urban metabolism and the collective
mind
and the memorable moment for me
was with uh dave dean and stephen
when we
um in the dot 2
we were just talking about like the cafe
next to the park with the red light and
the preference for light and we just
sort of started walking through
how we apply active inference and so
that was just a cool
discussion and this is an example is
like
yeah
like you know cities and states
the things that people care about
wouldn't it be useful if
we had a better way or a different way
to
talk about them
so that like it was just a fun
experience with you all and also it's
clearly a very relevant topic
yeah and you started when you started
doing some of that um
table manipulation stuff i in that in
that moment
sort of taking and manipulating and
moving things around i think that's
active inference and i think the other
my big thing was i wondered if i was
gonna
start
some kind of a conflict around the idea
of scale friendly but i didn't there
were actually people who actually took
that in into
into their lexicon and um considered it
and i i i here's the thing i think
sometimes in this
this setting
one of the things that we've
that the participants have evolved
around is the idea of introducing new
things
and i mean if they're ridiculous things
i mean we'll all give each other a hard
time but if we're introducing new things
it isn't just sort of shot down out of
hand people will try and find
ways to incorporate it and again that is
active inference
so
that was my big takeaway from this i was
really kind of impressed with the idea
that
um
bringing bringing something in that
isn't isn't necessarily citable
but something i think has to maybe be uh
included kind of like a housekeeping
rule
um and i'm no carl fristin but but
there were other people in on those live
streams who kind of went oh okay well
maybe we maybe we need to consider that
when we're talking in this context so
yeah
oh yeah not mentioned during this stream
was the symposium where we just
published the transcript with the doi so
that was very exciting and yeah i think
scale friendly
i i liked it because it almost it it
gives agency to the doer
instead of
passivity to the thinker it's like right
it's a skill-free framework it's like oh
great so it's in a museum and you pay
money to see it and it just figures
stuff out for you right it's scale free
it's like it's perfect
but it's like it's scale friendly
you can use this actively
but you got to be friendly to it as well
and use it like anybody else would use a
dynamic resource or asset
to
um it's like it's mount everest climbing
friendly
as far as climbing pins go
it's the one you want
so like it just totally refrains
yeah it's a hudson river moment honestly
it honestly is i mean that's not a
landing pad
but i mean it's it's friendly enough
right in
in in a moment of crisis
that's an example i think of what we
were what we were at least
entertaining doesn't mean that we could
have the math for it yet but we were
entertaining it yep
so yeah and everyone else who like
brought in
like
that was the fun of
the participatory approach and i know
that we're only beginning the voices and
the perspectives that we'll hear about
on the stream and the papers that
haven't been written yet
um
that's what's fun the beginner's
question
and the domain specific criticism
and the philosophical and the personal
and the way that it can come together
and we can do that
spontaneously and align with our values
and also
just
meet each other and
help others who are learning it's really
special that we got to do all these
streams
so
34.
the last paper that we read this year
which was the free energy principle it's
not about what it takes it's about what
took you there by axial constant
so
what a paper to
end the year with so axel is a
long-time collaborator with me on the in
for ants paper and some other work
and
so
i love
his writing and
the way that he's
talked about active imprints and
contributed to it in the philosophical
and in the ecological
and other areas
and the writing was engaging the
examples were clear
the labeling of what was called the
entailment problem
was one of the centerpieces of the paper
what's the entailment relationship
between minimizing free energy and life
is the strong claim
the sufficiency claim valid that if
you're minimizing free energy then
that's sufficient to say that the system
is alive
or
do systems
that are alive
by what definition but systems that are
alive
out of necessity
must they have done something looking
like minimize free energy
and just that nexus
and the uh
slide play
and the discussions that came out of
that just in the last few weeks
with you and stephen and others were
great
sid wrote the paper 34 did a number on
me
jk
yeah it was
a very interesting paper so
um
any comments on 34
well i think the best compliment i can
pay 34 is just to
ask people to make sure that they get a
chance to look at the paper
agreed
agreed all these papers i think are
read worthy and we hope that you'll
raise up important papers to read
next year
so i'll just kind of close with this
slide
um
yeah for 22.
what are you looking forward to
what paper should we read
who would like to join in who can we
invite what else could we do in dot coms
or other units
what other functions could the lab serve
if anyone's
looking to contribute or get involved
they really should all backgrounds and
time zones
if you just want to show up for even one
hour a month
or more
there will be an awesome place for you
and
if you want to interact
it would be
cool
so
um
[Music]
we had a great year
dean do you want to um add anything
about 22 or on any other point
well i think i mentioned the other day
that one of the things that i'm kind of
looking forward to is
is
i i don't i hate the word i hate the
word reset because it
it implies that somehow something was
already set but
and it's not
saying that i think that as as much as
as
we've had the privilege of learning this
year and and the privilege of having
people come in and explain what their
papers are and that sort of thing i i
hope that 22
reintroduces a little bit
more naivete
and a little bit more
i think i used the metaphor of adding
another walnut shell
i think
it's the biggest thing for me is that is
that everybody that has participated so
far has come in with a really open mind
they don't necessarily come in trying to
show how much they know and i think that
if we all sort of carry that forward
into 22
and really really um
appreciate that learning is about not
knowing first and foremost and if you
come into it even if even all the priors
that you have and all the experiences
and the backgrounds and the things
you've been able to figure out and
we seem to check a lot of that before we
before we go live and our and our song
begins to play
and i think that's a really really
healthy thing
and i think in 22
um
it will be the thing that will keep the
band together
for lack of a better way of describing
it i think
people will
people will know that every single time
they can show up they can show up with
with whatever background they have
because you keep saying it but i think
it's it's great in principle and it's
hard to overcome people need to see
evidence of that and i think
again i'm not trying to pump your tires
too much here but as long as we can keep
that front of mind and keep that culture
on display i think uh 22
is setting up to be something really
really amazing so
congratulations to you for
for doing this and like i said back in
april of this year when i
i don't want to get the name kill the
name but i i was at my cabin and i saw
you guys talking to chris white and i
just was like oh my goodness oh my
goodness oh my goodness what's what is
this
where where did this come from so that's
that's me let's say it's not necessarily
for everybody but for those who it is
for i think it's only a matter of time
before they're going to hear about this
and they're going to want to they're
going to want to get deeply involved in
it so well done
daniel ari
it was a very fun year um so big
thanks to all the organizers and just
everybody who is part of this
year's fun
and epistemic and pragmatic
value because it really was special
so
22 and beyond
right
great take it easy
peace have a